[Music]
reum what are they CVS curriculum V
whatever you call
them uh there are things that we use to
get jobs but I really feel like people
misunderstand their purpose a rum is to
get you an
interview that's it it's not there to
exhaustively cover every single
accomplishment you've ever had it's not
there to to supposedly brag or whatever
so what is in a good resume um and
according to what I I believe and what
I've seen out there and lessons I've
learned so uh I am going to tell a story
here I used to think that I had to have
the absolute perfect rum it if the rum
didn't cover every single thing I had
done had every accomplishment I had in
it I panicked that I was going to be you
know seen as a lesser than what I really
was and so was overly stressed about the
rum uh let me tell you why I think that
the
rum
is not as important as I used to think
it was or that so many people stress
they stress stress stress stress stress
about the rais again once again the sole
purpose of the risum the only reason for
a rum is to entice the person reading
the rism enough to get you an interview
that is it that's the only reason all
right now I'm going to follow that with
something else that's going to be very
controversial nobody cares about your
risum they just don't the people that
are actually required to read your resum
they're not going to read it the only
people who care about your resum is all
the crappy Recruiters on LinkedIn that
are trying to get a copy of the Raisor
from you so they can submit it and lock
you in so that they get a percentage of
the cut even if you organize and get
your job by yourself so by the way be
very careful who you give that raum to
do not I mean you can make it public but
if you explicitly give a raum to a
recruiter you are licensing that
recruiter to represent you in certain
companies and sometimes those recruiters
that's a separate video but sometimes
those recruiters will will stop you from
being able to even get the job yourself
in some places I know it's weird but
just just trust me on this one so what
is the ra the Ra's purpose is to get you
an interview it's also I'm going to I
want to be very explicit about this one
the raim's purpose is not to discover
you can I say that again the raim's
purpose is not so that people can find
you and I promise you all of that Panic
that you're feeling because everything
you can possibly do is not crammed into
your raisme all the right keywords all
the right technologies that you want to
come up in a Google search you that you
want to hit so that you can be found so
that you can get that that perfect job
out there because some AI or some some
random search engine out there actually
finds you and then sets up an interview
for you and sends it all because it's
all in your glorious resume it's a total
myth get over it that is not what they
are about right that is not what a r is
for a resum is to give to HR and to the
person with whom you have already set up
an interview okay and I'm going to talk
about this part a little bit longer than
I should
even though it should really go in a
separate
video the resum should be an
afterthought right I mean you should be
summarizing what's in there we'll talk
about what what goes into a good resumé
in just a bit but the purpose again of
the resumé is to kind of gives give a
conversational piece if you think about
if you if you imagine yourself if you
roleplay you know an overworked person
who's been given the responsibility to
interview you which has been me on
occasion and they they've got like 25
Rimes right and and you hit hear this
all the time make it keep it one page
don't go over I don't care how much
experience you have and the truth is it
really is true because these these
overworked people who are being forced
to read through these
raismes um to vet you or whatever
they're not first of all they're not
going to read them they don't care they
don't care I don't know how many times I
have been in an interview where somebody
asked me about something that was very
specifically delineated in my rais M
because they hadn't read it they didn't
say hey I saw this thing here because
they scan over they don't read it the
people that are going to be interviewing
you are not reading your risim they're
look they're they're interviewing you
for other reasons and this is why I
think it's so important when you that
you know this about about this the
process because then you'll know that
the RIS is there it's meant to be a
really high level like like like Rob's
you know Rob's best right like my best
moments that's what should go when
you're raising me high level that your
best absolute top moments they should be
you know it's like your highlights real
right that's what goes in your ra the
rum the main part of your R is your
highlights reel that's the thing that
someone's go oh well oh wow so if they
actually do scan it and see it you want
to put something in there that's like
really flashy that they're going to see
and it's going to that's going to give
them something to talk about because
that's the purpose of the rais it's not
to get you the interview I mean it is to
entice the interview out of somebody
like yeah let's give them an interview
like but honestly that's not even the
first thing that's going to that's going
to it is the purpose the purpose is to
get an interview but more more
specifically it's to make that interview
interesting once that you get the
interview right and so you can imagine
like you know you you've made contact
with this is how it goes down right
you've made contact with somebody um
either through a recruiter or you met
somebody from a Meetup or something like
that and they like oh man yeah it's like
yeah you sound like you're a good fit
for the job that we actually have right
now that's open would be really great to
have you and like and and then that
person who's not responsible PR hiring
you is going to say something like yeah
could you could you give me a raise me
and I'll you know I'll I'll load it by
my I'll load it by my manager right this
is how it goes down this is how jobs go
down this is how this is how jobs happen
and and then they'll be like so well I
have an update that's fine just whatever
and so you have this rais you've been
keeping up to date that's got your you
know your best hits in it and you you
know you send that over right away
before the the moment dies right away
you have to have that raison be ready
right away and that's a real thing that
people don't do you have to have the
best hits kind of think we're making a
video here I'll be in a sec so so then
you send that thing off to the to your
buddy that you made at the Meetup and
your buddy at the Meetup takes that PDF
or whatever and forwards that off
forwards that off to the manager now the
manager hasn't seen you the guy who's
the guy or girl who is responsible for
hiring you they don't know you they just
know that so and so who met you at this
media thinks you're a really good
position for this job and they've
recommended you and they're like well I
you know the manager is like well since
employment is all about trust I trust
this person and this person is giving me
a Raaz me and and now that person's put
themselves on the line by submitting
their rais because they're you know when
you make a recommendation about somebody
sometimes you have to say look I don't
know anything about them but they seem
like a nice person right no usually
you're making a referral just by giving
the raisin M off to somebody say hey hey
boss of me of mine you know here's
somebody that might be a good pit for
our team I just wanted to let you know
about them you hand off the rais me and
they're like huh and so that person is
reading through the rais of me and that
is where the magic of the Raaz of me
happens they're reading your baseball
card they're reading your best up
they're reading your hits and and the
person who has already referred you
because you made a friendship with them
has has already given you know produced
a little bit of trust in this person and
the manager is looking at the rais me
going going damn that's what you want
you want damn and then you want them to
think well what's this line Adam about I
need details here and now the manager is
incented to get you an interview and so
now you haven't even talked to HR yet
there's no HR in the process at all
there's no HR in the process there's no
HR and and the matter is like yeah we
need to get this person in here and talk
to them and said let me set that up and
so maybe the manager says to the person
who gave the referral that you met at a
Meetup that that that it you know they
set it up with HR and they they run down
all the bureaucratic crap which is
always this you know slog through the
mud no matter what but because you've
already made contact behind the scenes
with all the people and they've already
got the trust you've already greased all
the wheels of that of that machine and
it's going to work and so now your resum
now they'll say well and so that person
will either give the resum to HR and
they say hey can you send a cover letter
and send it to I go to we got to have
you officially apply to the HR so we can
get you the interview but but yeah you
looks really good and they want to meet
with you and then HR kind of is the last
one to know HR is the last one to know
HR is the one that gets told hey we want
to interview this person for this
position like well do you have that
position posted I'm like well not yet
and like well you need to post the
position so then so then they will post
the position to HR for you and then you
go in and get it they leave it out there
publicly for like a mandatory amount of
time legally for whatever reason and so
that other people can apply but they
already know who's going to apply
because they know you're there and they
say well we got to do this thing but you
got to interview and then they send you
through the process this is the stuff
that no one will tell you about the
hiring process that's how it actually
happens and it's it's not you know it's
it's it's not you know an
epismooth you know it it it is the way
things happen people know a person
they're friends with them they trust
them they recommend them and then they
get a job that's exactly how I got this
job true story I met I met somebody on
Twitch because I was going through the
transition after covid um and I they
said hey it would be great to have you
on our team I they took my resum to the
manager I had I had an interview I went
through the HR thing I was hired
seriously that is exactly how it
happened and that's how it can happen
for you I truly believe that I truly
believe that can happen for you I have
seen people get jobs by going to meetups
I've actually facilitated three or four
people getting jobs by going to a Linux
Meetup I went to a Linux convention uh
the southeast Linux convention Le Linux
Festival these last four days and I met
probably a dozen people uh all amazing
people um you know and but that's how
you get a job and that's a separate
video the the getting a job is not
blasting the world with raismes on
LinkedIn and everything and making sure
it's absolutely perfect it's got
everything you ever going to do so that
Google finds it and it's so some HR
those HR reps They Don't Care About You
the people who are going to look for
your risim online the AIS and the
machines and all those things they suck
they suck the people who are looking to
take your resum and they want to reach
out to you and say hey can I represent
you and you don't know anything about
them they are the enemy and you want to
avoid them like the plague because all
they're trying to do is Cash in on
getting you a job by and they you want
to avoid them you want to avoid those
people like the plague I'm serious you
want to find one or two recruiters maybe
who are recommended by people you know
in the industry again if and you're
finding out who those people are you've
already been through the mentorship
process you I mean I mean the submission
of a raate is like pretty late in the
game right so you definitely don't want
to do that you definitely don't want to
do that that late in the game you
definitely want at at the beginning of
the game you want you want to have the
context you want to be building a
professional Learning Network so again
so the rais is kind of an afterthought
raise is your best so what what goes in
the rum um the line items in the rum I
mean any of the traditional rum formats
are fine it really doesn't matter as far
as I'm concern I happen to maintain I
mean let's talk about the reason me
specific I personally think it should be
one page mine is two I think if you if
you've got over 10 years of experience
you're probably okay doing two pages um
however that's be I mean there's a
couple of criteria for the rais in my
opinion the number one thing about the
RM is it needs to be truthful right it
needs to be truthful it can't be an
exaggeration
number two the way you make it truthful
and you make it impressive is you put
metrics in it that you don't say is a
good learner you say uh implemented uh
12 node kubernetes lab in home lab to
gain uh kubernetes certification status
right lots of metrics the more details
the better people want details they
don't want fluff works well with people
no put you know uh
facilitated uh you know Communications
between two disperate teams that were
having difficulty doing blah blah blah
why again the purpose of the resum is to
promote conversation in an interview
that means when they see it they want to
hear the story so tell a story about who
you are what are your best hits do tell
the story of you in the rum in specific
terms not abstract terms and God I
cannot tell you how many resumés you
know that are just like fluffy crap and
filled with keywords they stuff it with
keywords because they want it to pull up
and like you're like why put all those
keywords in you just wasted my time
don't waste the person's time who's
reading the resum the resum should be
every single thing in the resum should
be exciting it should make them want to
talk to you and if you stuff the resum I
mean the education section this is why
you don't need every single place you've
ever been but this is also the reason
you should put things in there that
other people might not tell you to put
in there such as passion projects
everybody on the rais should have a
project section and it should say here
are the things I'm doing inic specific
detail to learn a thing I'm pursuing you
know this uh certification over here I I
completed hack the box at this level and
this thing here you know what I mean
it's like so you do have an education
section because you have to prove you
have a degree to get a job usually or
and in the education section you can say
um you know it's a kind of a tossup
about whether something should go in the
education section or the project section
but if you list your your projects
please make sure you do that you know uh
publication stuff if if the the only
again I'm speaking to potential
technologists here uh P paragraph to
make it rank in their crappy AI tool
yeah don't do that don't do that uh the
keywords are for the 0 point yeah zero
pixel F paragraph to make it yeah if if
if you look in my opinion if you are
padding your resum to make it look good
to an AI you're also broadcasting to
everybody that you have no idea how
getting a job works because it doesn't
work through some AI finding a raum a is
not how employment happens that's not
just me saying that that's learned with
Leon saying that like practically
yelling it into the mic employment
happens by establishing trust and trust
you can't thwart trust you've got to
figure out how to build that trust
whether it's through a recruiter or
through a secondary person or you meet
somebody directly who's hiring or you go
through an internship and they get to
see how awesome you are that's how
hiring happens it doesn't happen with
this cold calling crap if you're going
to cold call cold call to get an
understanding of what the the job is
about so that you can Target that job
and Target individuals doing that job to
be your potential mentors okay that and
then the rais is just an instrument that
is kind of the the focal point of
conversation that's being passed around
you want to make it easy to pass around
you want to make it easy to Gro you know
to digest and easy to see and um make it
easy to read man don't don't get crazy
use a sarap font people use son sarap
font on the razor man I'm like hell no
this is a piece of paper that has to be
read right so and then and then the last
thing I'll say about rumes is um tailor
the rum for the job so if it if the job
is slightly different than another job
you should actually prepare my opinion
you should prepare a specific resum for
every job you apply for because it's
just your highlights right so if you're
applying for an infrastructure
engineering job versus a backend systems
developer job you some of those those
things may may be the same but don't
submit the same razor to both of those
jobs you can do both of those jobs
sometimes they'll be the same job but
there you should have two completely
different raismes for that that have
your high points for that specific title
that match one for one the job
description and you will eventually get
to see the job description sometimes you
don't even see the job description till
after you got the job i' as happened
right because they you met somebody you
had the interview you go damn you're a
really good person for this job and they
say oh by the way here's the HR posting
for the job you know and so you know
this you definitely need to cater them
so then the question comes well I've
done so many things how do I keep track
of I'm going to have a story about this
this is how why I hate LinkedIn so at
one point I made a huge mistake I made a
huge monstrous mistake I thought that
LinkedIn could be my personal database
of everything I've ever done and that I
could use it and I could extract from it
the pieces that would go into a highly
precise specific Razor M for a specific
role in a specific job application right
I thought that I could you know go to
the API in LinkedIn and put it over here
and have have my CV or my my my Razor M
generated from that data you can't do it
you know why because link locks down
their API yeah the you guys are I'm
cattle f for LinkedIn they have a
tremendous API that's got a whole
formatted way to summarize a person that
is available to the people who mine you
but not to you I was like I'm never
using that again so there have been a
number of structured data formats uh to
put your risum you know you can use for
raum I happen to use uh we're going to
talk about this a little bit later but I
happen to use um let me go go show you
really quick uh hub.com rvx Rob
slcb uh and mine is pretty long the the
last one I did I'll show you um but what
you can do and this is going to be be
our goal here um my uh the goal here is
to have structured data the stuff that
would go into your CV or your rais and
yes um I have a summary of you know
different titles that I've had um but
again this is not the resum right this
is a database of all the stuff that I've
done and I'm not bragging here I just
want to show you that if you're like me
and you want to make sure that you don't
forget something cool that you did you
can maintain this sort of database
personal database in the form of a yamel
file and yeah it's pretty long it goes
all the all the way back to my mail uh
stuff honest to God it goes all the way
back to my to my mail job and this is
this also has uh nice things that people
have said about me and it I put
basically I built my own database and
then uh from the database we were able
to generate using this J.O program uh we
were able to take uh a thing and
generate a a a marked out an HTML file
and from that that HTML file uh we were
able to generate a PDF this is going to
be a flashbang I hope I don't break your
eyes I'm so sorry uh so so then I was
able to generate this thing now it is
two pages long I'm not going to spend a
lot of time on that I just wanted you to
see that the strategy for avoiding the
feeling like oh no I'm going to forget
something is to maintain a personal
database of your accomplishments uh and
that thing actually works for all kinds
of reasons outside of being a raisme it
also is a thing that you can go back to
if you maintain it if you get you know
get commit pretty regularly to it when
you do something really amazing you can
patch yourself on the back and you can
add a line item a very specific line
item to your own personal database of
cool stuff you've done and then when you
go to make the resum you have this
beautiful you know structured data file
that you can look at you can even
automate the creation by saying I want
this and this and this right but you
know just use Bim and copy it over and
you put that into a structure data file
and you generate a PDF from the
structure data file if you want to be
fancy otherwise just you write it in
word or whatever it doesn't matter the
point is is that all those little cool
things you've been doing are captured in
your own personal database of your
awesomeness and and you can actually
take a little moment to patch yourself
on the back when when you get a
compliment from somebody I actually I
actually keep in my data file nice
things that people say about me so and
the reason for that is because
occasionally somebody will want to know
a little bit more about you they might
want references right well I can
instantly create a references page just
from all the nice things that I've been
keeping that people have sent me in
twitch or they've said about me an email
or they've sent me hey can I put that in
my would you mind if I refers that and
they're like yeah and plus it just makes
you feel good like when you're feeling
really bad about yourself you can go
back and read all the good things that
you've done and the nice things people
have said about you can focus on that
instead of the things that are people
are saying bad about you so that all
goes in your own personal database in my
case I put it on a get repo I chose to
make it public uh and it's on GitHub now
the fact that it's if if you're going to
get discovered it's going to be through
GitHub it's not going to be because of
your Raisor it's going to be because of
GitHub if you're a technologist so so
having your CV you know in my opinion
having an open CV in inside of of GitHub
is a really great place to go because
you can then combine that you can
actually use that to generate uh your
you know in my case RBX Rob repo that
matches that's your landing page you
guys know about that right you we're
we'll talk about landing pages
separately but um so if you there GI up
has a special landing page uh that is
the same name as your account so if you
go SL RBX Rob in my case here um there
there's your landing page so this is the
page uh whatever is here um and I put
other things in here too some of which
are completely out of date I need to get
rid of it but the point is that becomes
this page that comes this page which is
kind of your most important uh sign to
show to the world that's what people
want to see about you they want to see a
summary of what your GitHub activity is
no matter what it is if you're in
technology um having an active GitHub is
an essential requirement in my opinion
and and I think that's the way to do it
and that even if that means that you're
just keeping your active notes in your
lab and the things you're experimenting
with maybe you keep your blog here so
that people see updates to your blog and
they get they see them get committed to
your GitHub and they can Follow You And
subscribe to you on GitHub even if your
final version of your blog gets pushed
to netlify or whatever um you know or
just hosted on GitHub they people can
follow your activity this is the most
important place to do a separate video
on this but that's also where you should
host your raisme and and or at least the
data that's going to go into their
specific rais that you're going to
prepare when somebody says okay well we
need you a rais to get the interview I
already talked to them they want to
interview you but they'd like to see a
rum like okay boom get him a raum in 10
minutes minutes before the iron gets
cold as they say and they've got it
they've got your raisme they want to see
you because it's got your best hits on
there and you're like damn this is cool
um so this video has has been longer
than I wanted but I the major takeaways
from this are raismes are to spont to
create conversation in an interview both
to promote the getting of the interview
uh you know but mostly to get people
excited about you so you can talk about
the interview they're not there to waste
people people don't care about your Reas
nobody cares about your rame you're the
only one so do not stress about your
rame you're the one who's going to oh my
God if my rais is not good I'm not going
to get a job no your rais doesn't need
to be your best hits but you've already
done you should have already done most
of the work to get the job uh and the
rais is just there to seal the deal and
to get the interview and to create
conversation interview right so so don't
let that be a source of worry for you I
people people overly stress about the
rais like crazy and by the way if you
have a mentor which you should at this
point because we talked about that
already way long ago if then your Mentor
is going to be able to look over your
resum damn that looks really good and
they'll be able to give you feedback on
your resum without having a job
interview if your Mentor maybe even
going to get you a job sometimes
sometimes your Mentor is in the career
and has contacts with people so again
the rum is is is secondary or tertiary
to you getting a job compared to all the
other things it should be one page it
should be your best hits it should be
drawn on a a regular uh a structured
database of your of everything you've
ever done that you maintain separately
and prepar on GitHub so people can be
notified when you have something cool to
say wouldn't it be cool if everybody
who's following you on GitHub saw that
you added a nice comment to your
somebody made a nice comment about you
on your live stream and you put that on
there and now everybody on GitHub just
got notified that somebody made a nice
comment about you because they're
following your GitHub those are that's
the reason to put GitHub as the source
for the data that goes into the rum but
again the rum is just coming from the
data like that uh I did I call it a brag
sheet I call a brag sheet all the time
um uh that's usually what I I I
deliberately refer I'm glad you
mentioned that Patrick close I I've
called it that in previous years um the
brag sheeet uh the brag sheet is just a
way of just like making sure that you
know you you have something to brag
about at the end of the year and so even
if you if it that database by the way we
should do a separate video on that
because the risim is just one
manifestation one view of the data if
you're know data science and databases
and stuff you know you have the database
and then you have different views into
the database right the resumé is one
specific very short view into that data
uh if you wanted to do a full-blown CV
because you're going to Academia or
something like that you could do that
you could have multiple views into your
little database and I I think it should
just be structured data because you can
edit with a file um materialized view
yeah there there are people who do it in
different ways there are people who uh
get you know downright crazy and make
their own personal database I don't I
think that's pushing it some people say
well aren't you going to use the data
model there's already you know rais a
May uh there there's already you know
JJs there's like a ton of models they
all suck so you develop your own model
for what you should think to go in there
I personally prefer yamel because it's
just it's so readable as it is and I can
maintain it really easy if it's hard to
maintain if I have to spin up my
database or my database goes down I have
to back up my database or something like
that I'm not going to maintain it but if
I maintain it as a structured data file
which is why we have to cover structured
Data before we do this um then I think
it's just easier it's easier for you to
maintain it's easier for anybody to see
if somebody wants to summarize your
database they can just scan down on the
file they don't have to set up the whole
database and everything people over
engineer things all the time so so we
will do a separate uh several videos
about how to make that structure data
file uh that is the rais or the the
whatever the personal data file is going
to be uh the project that we do to learn
yaml and to learn uh later on go and
some other things in order to generate
the thing um so that will be there'll be
other videos on that all right is that
enough
does that
enough okay